<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-28T21:57:31+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poemaday/feed.xml</id><title type="html">poemADAY</title><subtitle>A blog: Teach, Talk and Learn Poetry</subtitle><author><name>Sandip Baidya</name><email>sandipbaidya17@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">O’Keefe Shows How To Own Grief</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-28/Christin-O'keefe-Three-Months" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="O’Keefe Shows How To Own Grief" /><published>2020-12-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-28/Christin-O'keefe-Three-Months</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-28/Christin-O'keefe-Three-Months">&lt;h2 id=&quot;three-months-after&quot;&gt;Three months after&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;To want to disappear, is different from wanting to die&lt;/code&gt;. To be honest, I’m writing about this poem, after reading and listening to it many times today, because I feel something’s either about to arrive, or has arrived but preparing, or ready to collapse, like a dam. The nature of this impending disaster feels gloomy. And so, I have been listening to this poem, to prepare myself. Like how you sit on the bed, naked, pressured with the likeliness of this moment leading up to sex, so you must sit or lay down in a different manner. You sit there with legs poised in manners that you wouldn’t, under normal circumstances, preparing preparing preparing your body. I do the same, except instead of excitedness, happiness and lust, today I feel hollow. &lt;strong&gt;Listen to her poem &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pF_N_pZa2WM&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’keefe attempts to express the nature of this feeling by distinguishing &lt;em&gt;wanting to disappear&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;wanting to die&lt;/em&gt;. I feel hollow, and not sad. Meaning, this could’ve easily been sadness but it’s not. It’s closer to being sad, yet when you truly look, its actually not sadness at all; like when you magnify between two digits, you can see an infinite sea of numbers sitting between them, thus making you realise how wide a seemingly small difference can be. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;To move to somewhere, where no one knows you&lt;/code&gt; is wanting to distance yourself so far away from everything you’ve known, that you stop being who you are. Because, you are mostly what things around you are. Or not? I don’t know, I’m not spending too much time on speculating because today I read this poem as if it was my own baby; my own making. I do not question how the baby came to be, I simply resign to take care of it, till at some point, I can not &amp;amp; then I’ll probably move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grief-the-friend-you-cant-shake-off&quot;&gt;Grief: The friend you can’t shake off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;To elope with this grief who is not your enemy. This grief who maybe now is your best friend.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I’ve felt this. The power of grief is so intense that you no longer look for means to shut it out; you carry it everywhere, nurture it and let it run its full course over you. That is the only solution. Any thing that may come to rescue you from it, is fleeting. This is where poetry becomes interesting. I read this poem, I’m still reading this poem as the year 2020 is coming to an end, and thus has born in me this unshakeable grief. This poem becomes my moment. This poem becomes my everything, perhaps my guiding light to wade through this jungle of grief. O’keefe, in her poem knows the substance of this grief, that’s why she’s able to talk about it so beautifully. My grief is abstract yet strong, and her voice in this poem is my altar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;This grief who is your husband&lt;/code&gt;, that’s how close this grief is. It’s not just a lover who you give yourself to, at night in loving embrace, in security, but rather a husband that you’re married to–the grief is in a matrimonial contract with you. It’s official, it’s strong, it’s a two-person thing. This grief wakes up early morning and makes &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;you your cold thankless breakfast&lt;/code&gt; and you better eat it, you owe yourself and the grief this sustenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;To go to that place where every surface is a blade.
A sharp thing on which to hang your sorry flesh to feel something, anything, other than this.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This imagery is the most brutal but honest one. This self assault and punishment when dealing with grief is a strange feat by the &lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;. You may be reading this and you may or may not be sad, or utterly sad, or devastatingly sad, or just depressed, or something else, yet I want you to hang on to these words, because somedays you will feel like this. You &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; feel that every surface during this period, is blade. Is hurtful. Is a mockery. Is pain hurled at yourself. Is grief essentially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ps&quot;&gt;PS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please reach out to someone who cares for you when it’s too much and becomes too difficult to handle. Blades are okay. Too many blades are not okay, sometimes you need to rest and a bed full of blades is too inhumane. I understand that I was supposed to be speculative when it comes to discussing poems, and I somewhat failed to do that here, but through this I wanted to show you the power of poetry and why it is essential to us. Analysis is a beautiful process, but if a poem moves you beyond something, then you must grab that feeling. You must let yourself feel over analysis. Make that choice. Always choose &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; something over not feeling at all. Sometimes a poem will become a part of you, and my only wish for you is to let it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sandip Baidya</name></author><category term="Cristin-O'Keefe-Aptowicz" /><summary type="html">Three months after</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-28-Grief.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-28-Grief.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Vijay Nambisan has made ducks mysterious for me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-14/Vijay-Nambisan-Duck-Poems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vijay Nambisan has made ducks mysterious for me" /><published>2020-12-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-14/Vijay-Nambisan-Duck-Poems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-14/Vijay-Nambisan-Duck-Poems">&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-buoyancy&quot;&gt;1. Buoyancy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever noticed that you’re wandering with music in ears somewhere quiet in a park with very few people around and suddenly you feel legless? And then you get curious because you can’t possibly be taking this long, beautiful and serene walk without legs! You probably feel what the ducks feel and Vijay Nambisan (a brilliant poet I discovered yesterday) captures this stunningly in his poem &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://poetry.sangamhouse.org/2016/07/duck-poems-by-vijay-nambisan/&quot;&gt;Duck Poems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ducks have, in water, a feeling that they are  
Not quite all there
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you look down to see if you’re actually legless or not. Now now, all this happens within a very small interval of time (the dreaded &lt;em&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that you learned in Physics)  so it feels more dramatic in the moment than how it reads here.
And when you’ve confirmed that you are infact not legless, you look up and you feel this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;And so when I look up  
I return where I belong, after long separation.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-original-sin&quot;&gt;2. Original Sin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nambisan names the second part of his poem, &lt;em&gt;Original Sin&lt;/em&gt;. He calls out our descendants, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mothers' mothers&lt;/code&gt; for wanting to come out of the ocean, forsaking &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;amniotic contentment&lt;/code&gt;. He thinks that this act of abandoning security that one finds in the earliest stages of life, is the &lt;strong&gt;Original Sin&lt;/strong&gt; and we’re all generational products of that sin. He calls this sin to have been preceeded by a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;primeval notion&lt;/code&gt; which drove our mothers’ mothers to desire &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;suffering&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bliss&lt;/code&gt;. Who knew, from ducks, one could spin out such an interesting woeful but adventurous tale of genesis. Nambisan is a genius, as you can see. I love how he indirectly calls us the byproducts of the need to have suffering over bliss. It’s encoded in us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-14-Vijay-Nambisan-ducks-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-double-bill&quot;&gt;3. Double Bill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part of the poem has used, by far the most ingenuous way of describing “two faceted way of living”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Only they  
When they look down can see both halves,  
The webbed and the unwebbed.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the duck looks down underwater or on land, towards its feet–the entryway to the double life much like how a person can always look into themselves and tell the doubles apart from each other. The tragedy of this double life is the constant hiding :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A duck  
Maybe thinks she has reason to hide  
What she does with her feet. She must float  
For no one must know she can walk on water.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this stanza so much because it uses such a sweet image of a duck’s life to talk about two-facetedness. We all lead double lives (or multiple lives), it’s a human condition and it made me so happy when I read Nambisan’s way of talking about it. Truly a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-mach-duck&quot;&gt;4. Mach Duck&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mach means a ratio. A ratio of speed of body over the speed of sound in the surrounding medium. So for e.g. 2 mach in air would mean the body is travelling at twice the speed of sound in air. Mach Duck therefore, is the niftiest title I’ve heard in such a long time. In this part of the poem, Nambisan is sweet-innocently rambling and I found it very cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I should like to know, but  
Water is another medium for me, too,  
And if I stooped and immersed my head  
I should think of something else entirely,  
Probably having nothing to do with ducks. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-lapres-midi-dun-canard&quot;&gt;5. L’apres Midi d’un Canard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translates to &lt;em&gt;The afternoon of a duck&lt;/em&gt; and wow. Even if Nambisan had finished the whole poem after that line, I would’ve been mind-blown. This sub-title itself packs so much imagery. Whenever I visit the countryside, I feel a restless desire to explore nature through the bodies of animals and a duck’s one of them. How amazing it’d be to flap out of a bird coop and flap my way to the nearest pond. Rest my plumes on the softness of water-cut pebbles by the shore, find clams and slowly break them in halves and suck the juice out of them. To take a swim and feel like the middle child of day and night as the afternoon sun basks me from the top and the coldness from the pond creeps up my underbelly. What great joy to see my webbed feet catch algae and insects in the ripples of water. Dipping my head like a pilgrim and watch the underwater world become a temporary escape. To feel both of the land and the water and to flap back home as the afternoon comes to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nambisan writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;They lure the viewer into hyperbole  
Just by stepping off, as if they did not know  
That turbid, weed-choked pond contained  
All they had forgotten of their fate.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This poem has made me love ducks even more. I hope you enjoyed reading this very crafty poem and would feel motivated to read more poems by &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/article/909672/a-collection-of-vijay-nambisans-poems-allows-us-the-opportunity-to-reframe-his-legacy&quot;&gt;him&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sandip Baidya</name></author><category term="Vijay-Nambisan" /><summary type="html">1. Buoyancy</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-14-Vijay-Nambisan-ducks-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-14-Vijay-Nambisan-ducks-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mary Oliver Writes for the wild heart</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-12/Mary-Oliver-wild-geese" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mary Oliver Writes for the wild heart" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-12/Mary-Oliver-wild-geese</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-12/Mary-Oliver-wild-geese">&lt;h3 id=&quot;wild-geese&quot;&gt;“Wild Geese”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first read &lt;strong&gt;Wild Geese&lt;/strong&gt; I felt calm. When I &lt;a href=&quot;https://onbeing.org/poetry/wild-geese/&quot;&gt;heard&lt;/a&gt; her recite the poem, I felt tamed. Read the poem &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phys.unm.edu/~tw/fas/yits/archive/oliver_wildgeese.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
This poem plucked me out of my New Delhi small room and dropped me in the valleys of my hometown. Mary has already invented teleportation and all she uses are mere words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her very first sentence is coaxing. It’s like she knows that us readers, on the very inside, are tired people. She knows that we pretend to be good, learned and respectable. She cuts straight to the point &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;You do not have to be good&lt;/code&gt; and that right there is good enough of a promise for me. This opening is like the shallow waters that you want to sink yourself deeper into because you feel less scared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;You do not have to walk on your knees
for a hundred miles through the desert repenting.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How kind. She’s asking us to not punish ourselves for too long for something that we did. She calls on the quality of being human, of erring. These lines remind me of the characters in the Hindu mythological stories where punishments are taken very seriously. Where, in order to repent and salvage oneself, years of pain must be afflicted to both mind and body and sacrifices must be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you’re not (only) good and you’ve stopped the unending journey of repentance, what must you do then? Oliver suggests, to love. Love what the body wants. I still feel mesmerized when I read the lines: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;You only have to let the soft animal of your body love what it loves.&lt;/code&gt; Love beyond, love even if it’s unconventional, love what YOU want to love. &lt;em&gt;Animal of the body&lt;/em&gt; refers to something innate in humans, something that doesn’t perform within the structures of a society and hence, allow yourself to love like the &lt;strong&gt;soft&lt;/strong&gt; animal inside you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And she promises that she’s here for us. She promises to sit with us and listen to our despairs. In exchange, she trusts us enough to share her own woes with us. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Tell me about despair, yours, and I will tell you mine.&lt;/code&gt; What better way to caste off years of bitterness and shadows of gloom than to find a friend and exchange woes. What better way than that to bond because when you share, you realise how awfully hard you have been on yourself. How living has been cut off because there’s too much weight and that you must work now, to unburden all that because the world will keep on moving. It doesn’t wait for you to catch up after you’ve decided to switch yourself off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she takes you back to the nature. Teleportation working like magic in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Meanwhile the sun and the clear pebbles of the rain
are moving across the landscapes,
over the prairies and the deep trees,
the mountains and the rivers.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection that she attempts to create between the expansive nature and the readers is something I truly cherish. I find great joy in losing myself in nature and every single time, I wish I could see through the eyes of the wild animals that dwell forever in it. This year when I visited my hometown in Tripura, the ground beneath me shook and I felt bewitched at the wild unravelling in front of me. It felt like I couldn’t ever belong. That if I ever did belong, I could only, by being something unhuman. &lt;strong&gt;A goose perhaps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-12-Mary-Oliver-Wild-geese-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Meanwhile the wild geese, high in the clean blue air,
are heading home again.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find so much recluse in her words. If words had the power to become home, this poem would have been my home and I, its forever citizen. Mary tells us the power of the imagination that this world has bestowed on its beings. She wants us to never forget that life can only become more adventurous from here, no matter what. And that regardless of what happens, our souls will always have a place in the family of the nature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;over and over announcing your place
in the family of things.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A family that we can always come back to. I hope you enjoyed reading this poem as much I did. Mary Oliver has a very precious way of writing about lived human experiences and the nature in a calm convulated way. She truly is a brilliant poet. Read more poems from her &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/mary-oliver&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sandip Baidya</name></author><category term="Mary-Oliver" /><summary type="html">“Wild Geese”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-12-Mary-Oliver-Wild-geese.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-12-Mary-Oliver-Wild-geese.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Whatever it takes to be happy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-09/Tishani-Doshi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whatever it takes to be happy" /><published>2020-12-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-09/Tishani-Doshi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/2020-12-09/Tishani-Doshi">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-be-happy-in-101-days&quot;&gt;“How To Be Happy In 101 Days”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title is the most interesting part with the promise of an end goal–happiness. The poem breaks out into a very poetic list of things that you are advised to do. I wonder if each of these things in the list carry an individual power to make you happy or whether only upon the completion of all the tasks in the list, could you achieve happiness. Read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/152737/how-to-be-happy-in-101-days&quot;&gt;poem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list starts by demanding something that feels very simple on the face of it; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adore stone&lt;/code&gt; as if asking you to love someone immobile, someone very wooden and boring and incompatible with yourself. Throughout this first stanza, Doshi is advising us to give time to something or someone that you generally find less entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She pulls sarcasm when she puts &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;look for utilitarian values in violence&lt;/code&gt; in the list. Surely a very dark way of saying “waste your time finding something that isn’t even there.” As I kept advancing through the list, I realised that I’ve got the answer to the very first question I had asked; These tasks can not individually make one happy because as humans we have a tendency to rely on instant gratification and none of the things in the list so far, has given me a quick dose of delight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;use the knife lustily&lt;/code&gt; is such an intimate activity. This reminds me of the times when I sit outside in the balcony, alone, and slowly peel back the skins of oranges, devouring them seductively. Cutting bread for the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;undending hunger of dogs&lt;/code&gt; feels honest to me. It’s an act that must be done over and over again because once is not enough even if it instantly delights the human heart. You can not wash hands with suffering by one good act of kindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Renounce your house. Take just one  
object with you. Slip it in your pocket.  
Marvel at how a simple thing can  
connect the variegated skeins of time.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She’s asking us to do something so heart-breaking–to renounce the house. Not renounce it like “oh, I’m gonna go out for a walk” or like “I’m going on a vaction so the house will be empty.” The very house that took years to essemble with its objects and people and memories must be forsaken but she allows one object. That &lt;strong&gt;object will become our house&lt;/strong&gt; for the rest of 101 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;On the 99th  day, you must surrender  
this object, but until then feel free  
to attach sentiment to it.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much about letting go. Does happiness come through learning to let go? because Doshi later in the poem asks us to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;find a tree to hang your dead&lt;/code&gt; and their belongings. Now, letting go is not the same as forgetting, but rather it’s a means to unburdening. This is a recurring theme throughout the poem. Doshi continuously demands for poessesions (both the tangible and intangible) to be let go of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She’s asking to reconnect with the nature to feel how much larger this world really is than the self (I think its a satire on internet and the people of the internet). Like really really reconnect with the nature which is evident in the lines:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Rub the smooth globes of their roots  
in our palms before biting in to their hearts.  
Lean backwards and listen to the slippery  
bastard of your own arrhythmic heart.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like how she says &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;remind yourself that you feel pain&lt;/code&gt; because that’s how you know that you must be alive. Pain is the thread that connects us to reality. It is the scream that keeps us awake. One of my favourite lines is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;stain your fingers in ink&lt;/code&gt;. Ink is something that is very close to my heart. When I doodle or write poems on my notebooks in ink, I feel the world around me crumble to nothing. Ink for me is the highest vessel of intimacy and peacefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think that killing must be truly horrific. Many summers ago, as I sat fishing at the brink of a wild pond and threw the bait in, I caught my first Telapia. I beat its head hard on the ground and watched life slowly leave its eyes and it didn’t feel horrible. I felt like an observer. I watched the feeble grip of life weakening with a strange interest. Doshi advises &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Do not close your eyes&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know clavicles meant collar bones in plurality. I agree with her. Offer them to someone. In fact, keep on offering them, its a pleasure that one should be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she asks to offer your children to a stranger or if you’re childless, offer the person you love best, I felt a pang of sadness. It felt like betrayal on Doshi’s part. Why would you ask of something so cruel? Is this what will secure happiness in 101 days? Later, when I read these lines over and over again, I realised something. I think she’s asking us to give our loves some room to breathe. This reminded me of the song &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RBumgq5yVrA&quot;&gt;Let Her Go&lt;/a&gt; by Passenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Spend the night in the cemetary&lt;/code&gt;  and allow yourself the fear of the deads by hearing their laughs. I think she honestly means it. No metaphor there. However, this is something that I will never be able to do. I watched a horror movie last summer and the images still haunt me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doshi asks to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;not bother with the stars&lt;/code&gt; because they are for the romantics who apparently aren’t happy people. What a call out. Skip this step if you’re a poet. These tasks that she enlists are each so difficult to perform and somehow happiness feels like a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;How little you know yourself&lt;/code&gt;, a challenge against instincts to know how much we know ourselves. I’ve always been very jealous of people who &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; themselves. Something about the quality of being decisive and instinctive feels arousing to me. Reminds me of how Elio envies Oliver for saying “I know myself too well” in CMBYN and I feel that. Doshi however, understands that its uncommon to be naturally instinctive thus she asks us to allow mistakes : &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;try the other path in order to understand&lt;/code&gt;. She wants us to know that instincts are built, not naturally inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going through so many arduous tasks, our sublimation is afoot but first we must meditate. I guess meditating is meant to balm all the hurt that the previous tasks have afflicted on our minds. She’s asking us to stabilize ourselves before we graduate this course of happiness. Surprisingly, the quest of giving up hasn’t ended yet. She wants us to give up our bodies to tigers (here tigers must mean someone familiar) and if not tigers then some other hungry creature. She draws focus on the importance of losing our bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The time has come&lt;/strong&gt; to bury that one treasured thing we had acquired before renouncing our houses. It is the 99th day. The journey has been far too difficult than what I had imagined. Her last piece of advice is the most important one throughout the list. She wants us to search for a mirror (a very ordinary plane mirror), strip in front of it and relflect. It’s funny how, after going through so much, it is &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; who can only tell whether I’m happy. There’s no score card, no evalutation report, there’s nothing that could ever tell whether you were successful in attaining happiness. And this is what scares me. This subjectivity with which life must be lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sigh-sigh-sigh-sigh&quot;&gt;Sigh Sigh Sigh Sigh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tishani Doshi’s poems are pensive. I love how guideful this poem is. What’s more fascinating is when I approached the end of the poem, I realised that this poem is a mere scaffolding. We each, must find our own list of things to do to attain happiness in 101 days. I hope this poem encourages you to read more poems by &lt;a href=&quot;https://tishanidoshi.weebly.com/&quot;&gt;Doshi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sandip Baidya</name></author><category term="Tishani-Doshi" /><summary type="html">“How To Be Happy In 101 Days”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-9-Tishani-Doshi.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/poemaday/assets/images/2020-12-9-Tishani-Doshi.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>